

Deutsches Primatenzentrum GmbH, Kellnerweg 4, 37077, Göttingen, Germany

■ NSirmpilatze@dpz.eu | 🏕 www.nsirmpilatze.com | 🖸 niksirbi | 🛩 @niksirbi | 📂 Nikoloz Sirmpilatze

Research Interest

My research focuses on the effects of anesthesia on brain function – a topic that I explore with neuroimaging techniques, including functional Magnetic Imaging (fMRI) and in vivo 2-photon calcium imaging. I collect and analyze neuroimaging data from multiple mammalian species – including humans, various non-human primates and rats. I am particularly interested in the neural activity patterns that arise across various depths of anesthesia, either spontaneously or in reaction to sensory stimulation.

Education

German Primate Center - Functional Imaging Lab

Göttingen, Germany

PhD in Neuroimaging

May 2017 - Sep. 2021

- Thesis title: Functional imaging of the anesthetized brain in primates and rodents
- · Supervisor: Prof. Dr. Susann Boretius
- Final grade: Summa cum laude

Georg-August University of Göttingen - IMPRS for Neurosciences

Göttingen, Germany Sep. 2015 - Apr. 2017

MSc in Neuroscience

- · Thesis title: The temporal stability of BOLD fMRI measurements in medetomidine-anesthetized rats
- Supervisor: Prof. Dr. Susann Boretius
- Final grade: excellent 1.1 (1.0 down to 5.0)

Aristotle University of Thessaloniki

Thessaloniki, Greece

DOCTOR OF MEDICINE (MD)

• Final grade: excellent 9.43/10

Oct. 2009 - Jul. 2015

Advanced Courses & Workshops.

Sep. 2019 Brainhack Comparative MRI , PRIME-DE Global Collaboration Workshop	London, UK
Feb. 2018 Introduction to Data Science with python, GGNB graduate school	Göttingen, Germany

May 2017 Regression Modeling in R, Leibniz Science Campus Primate Cognition

Göttingen, Germany

Nov. 2016 Laboratory Animal Science Course on Primates, European Primate Network (EUPRIM-NET)

Göttingen, Germany

Oct. 2016 Laboratory Animal Science (FELASA Category B), Central Animal Facility, University Medical Center

Göttingen, Germany

Stipends & Awards_

2019	Magna cum Laude Merit Award & Educational Stipend, 27 th Annual Meeting of the ISMRM	Montreal, Canado
2017	Student Support Program , 34 th Annual Meeting of the ESMRMB	Barcelona, Spair

2015 Full MSc Student Scholarship, German Academic Exchange Service (DAAD) Germany

2010 **Undergraduate distinction**, Yearly Stipend from the State Scholarships Foundation of Greece (IKY) Greece

Academic Service

PRIME-RE (PRIMatE Resource Exchange)

MAINTAINER AND CONTRIBUTOR Sep. 2019 - present

- PRIME-RE is an open resource exchange platform for non-human primate neuroimaging: prime-re.github.io
- It is a community effort, initiated by the PRIME-DE (PRIMatE Data Exchange) consortium

Neurizons Conference

2017 - 2020 ORGANIZER

- Neurizons is a biennial student-organized neuroscience conference
- Was responsible for graphic design in 2018 and led the migration to an online format in 2020

Teaching Experience

Teaching Assistant for Introduction to MRI/fMRI

IMPRS FOR NEUROSCIENCES MSc PROGRAM

Göttingen, Germany

2017 - 2019

- · Gave tutorials and hands-on method courses of fMRI acquisition and analysis
- Workload: approx. 1 week per year for 3 years

Supervisor for Master Student

Göttingen, Germany

IMPRS FOR NEUROSCIENCES MSc PROGRAM

Oct. 2018 - Mar. 2019

• Dmytro Nesterenko: Resting state connectivity and negative BOLD responses

Supervisor for Lab Rotations

Göttingen, Germany

IMPRS FOR NEUROSCIENCES MSc PROGRAM

2019 - 2020

- Hanna Dubrovska: Ipsilateral negative BOLD response during the motor task in the HCP dataset
- · Anna Liashenko: Changes in resting state functional connectivity after the neurofeedback training of anterior midcingulate cortex (aMCC)
- Duration of each rotation: 8 weeks

Community Teaching Assistant for Medical Neuroscience

Online

MOOC OFFERED BY DUKE UNIVERSITY THROUGH WWW.COURSERA.ORG

Jan. - Mar. 2013

· Monitored student forums and answered questions

Teaching Assistant for Neuroanatomy

Thessaloniki, Greece

LABORATORY OF DESCRIPTIVE ANATOMY, ARISTOTLE UNIVERSITY MEDICAL SCHOOL

Feb. - May 2011

• Assisted during practical course on brain dissection

Skills

MRI acquisition Familiar with **Bruker** (Paravision) and Siemens Prisma platforms

MRI analysis FSL, ANTS, nipype, Freesurfer, Connectome Workbench, AFNI, BrainVoyager, nilearn

Optical Methods *In vivo* 2-photon calcium imaging in rat neocortex

Programming Python, R, Bash, git, LTFX

Laboratory Animals Rodent handling, anesthesia, surgery, stereotaxic injections

Languages Greek, Georgian, English, German, Russian

Research Output_

PEER-REVIEWED PUBLICATIONS

- 1. **Sirmpilatze**, N., Baudewig, J. & Boretius, S. Temporal stability of fMRI in medetomidine-anesthetized rats. *Scientific Reports* **9**, 16673. ISSN: 2045-2322 (Nov. 2019).
- 2. Messinger, A., **Sirmpilatze**, N., Heuer, K., Loh, K. K., Mars, R. B., Sein, J., Xu, T., Glen, D., Jung, B., Seidlitz, J., Taylor, P., Toro, R., Garza-Villarreal, E. A., Sponheim, C., Wang, X., Benn, R. A., Cagna, B., Dadarwal, R., Evrard, H. C., Garcia-Saldivar, P., Giavasis, S., Hartig, R., Lepage, C., Liu, C., Majka, P., Merchant, H., Milham, M. P., Rosa, M. G., Tasserie, J., Uhrig, L., Margulies, D. S. & Klink, P. C. A collaborative resource platform for non-human primate neuroimaging. *NeuroImage* **226**, 117519. ISSN: 1053-8119 (2021).
- 3. Hafner, G., Guy, J., Witte, M., Truschow, P., Rüppel, A., **Sirmpilatze**, N., Dadarwal, R., Boretius, S. & Staiger, J. F. Increased Callosal Connectivity in Reeler Mice Revealed by Brain-Wide Input Mapping of VIP Neurons in Barrel Cortex. *Cerebral Cortex*. bhaa280. ISSN: 1047-3211 (Nov. 2020).
- 4. Lohrberg, M., Winkler, A., Franz, J., van der Meer, F., Ruhwedel, T., **Sirmpilatze**, N., Dadarwal, R., Handwerker, R., Esser, D., Wiegand, K., Hagel, C., Gocht, A., König, F. B., Boretius, S., Möbius, W., Stadelmann, C. & Barrantes-Freer, A. Lack of astrocytes hinders parenchymal oligodendrocyte precursor cells from reaching a myelinating state in osmolyte-induced demyelination. *Acta Neuropathologica Communications* **8,** 224. ISSN: 2051-5960 (Dec. 2020).

CONSORTIUM PUBLICATIONS

- 1. Milham, M. *et al.* Accelerating the Evolution of Nonhuman Primate Neuroimaging. *Neuron* **105,** 600–603. ISSN: 0896-6273 (Feb. 2020).
- 2. Gau, R. *et al.* Brainhack: Developing a culture of open, inclusive, community-driven neuroscience. *Neuron* **109**, 1769–1775. ISSN: 0896-6273 (2021).

CONFERENCE CONTRIBUTIONS

- 1. **Sirmpilatze**, N., Baudewig, J., Mylius, J., Golkowski, D., Ranft, A., Ilg, R., Paasonen, J., Gröhn, O. & Boretius, S. fMRI mapping of anesthesia-induced burst suppression across multiple mammalian species in 15th European Molecular Imaging Meeting (virtual) Online Talk (2020).
- 2. **Sirmpilatze**, N., Baudewig, J., Mylius, J., Golkowski, D., Ranft, A., Ilg, R. & Boretius, S. *Using BOLD fMRI to map anesthesia-induced burst suppression in humans and non-human primates* in 27th Annual Meeting of the International Society for Magnetic Resonance in Medicine Talk (2019).
- 3. **Sirmpilatze**, N., Baudewig, J. & Boretius, S. *Are fMRI measurements in medetomidine-anesthetized rats tempo-rally stable?* in 27th *Annual Meeting of the International Society for Magnetic Resonance in Medicine* Digital Poster (2019).
- 4. **Sirmpilatze**, N., Baudewig, J., Kötz, K. & Boretius, S. *Optimizing medetomidine anesthesia for fMRI in rats* in 11th Forum of Neuroscience, Federation of European Neuroscience Societies Poster (2018).
- 5. **Sirmpilatze**, N., Baudewig, J., Kötz, K. & Boretius, S. *The temporal stability of BOLD fMRI measurements in medeto-midine anesthetized rats* in 34th Annual Meeting of the European Society for Magnetic Resonance in Medicine and Biology Poster (2017).

OPEN DATASETS

- 1. **Sirmpilatze**, N. & Klink, P. C. *RheMAP: Non-linear warps between common rhesus macaque brain templates* (Zenodo, May 2020).
- 2. **Sirmpilatze**, N., Baudewig, J. & Boretius, S. *Temporal stability of fMRI in medetomidine-anesthetized rats* (Open-Neuro, Nov. 2019).